Alright, בוקר טוב Boker tov from snowy Riverdale and welcome to עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. We're on the top of דף Daf 15.
We've looked at the משנה Mishnah at the bottom of דף Daf
14 ב, Bet, and we looked at what, how are our interactions
with the עובדי כוכבים Ovdei kochavim around us vis-a-vis our animals. The
משנה Mishnah instructed us with two things: if it's a בהמה דקה,
Behemah dakah, what we call like a more light kind of animal,
sheep, goat, etc., then there are places where there's a custom to
sell and a custom not to sell. It's discussed as a custom
as opposed to the בהמה גסה, Behemah gasah, cows, horses,
that the משנה Mishnah tells us, אין מוכרין בהמה גסה. Ein mocherin
behemah gasah. And this is supposedly across the board, we do not
sell these kind of animals to the non-Jews. Now the גמרא Gemara
on top of 15
עמוד א, Amud aleph, six lines from the top, is going to
start a discussion of why, why so? ובכל מקום אין מוכרין בהמה
גסה, U’ve’chol makom ein mocherin behemah gasah, good? Yeah.
מאי טעמא Mai ta’ama asks the גמרא. Gemara.
The issues around בהמה דקה Behemah dakah were around רבעיה, Reva’iyah,
bestiality and our concerns of humans' relationships with the animals. I know,
I'm assuming here it sounds like bizarre, right, this is even a
concern?
But at least as far as jokes growing up in Israel, this
was always like a spoken thing of shepherds in the mountains, whatever.
That things do happen, so it makes less sense in New York
but possibly
there
were things like that or maybe our text would not speak to
it.
With the בהמה גסה, Behemah gasah, with the big animals, that is
not our concern, says the גמרא, Gemara, דלרבעיה לא חיישינן. D'le’reva’iyah lo
chaishinan. מעביד בה מלאכה חיישינן. Ma’avid bah melacha chaishinan. So what we
are concerned about is not the bestiality but possibly מלאכה.
Melacha. And we’ll see that the גמרא Gemara is having a discussion
around working these animals on שבת. Shabbat.
It doesn't come full circle to what possibly can be the reason
and maybe what it is beyond these concerns is that the בהמה
דקה Behemah dakah is more associated with nomadic culture and the בהמה
גסה Behemah gasah more with people that live permanently and therefore we
come into issues of giving land away in the land of Israel
on a more permanent basis. But the גמרא Gemara does not go
there. The גמרא Gemara stays right now in a discussion on worrying
about using these animals on שבת. Shabbat. And we immediately have to
ask the question, which the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, what
does it matter if we sold the animal? It's not ours anymore,
so let it work whenever it wants to work.
Eight lines from the top on 15 דף א Daf a עמוד
א. Amud aleph. וניעביד כיון דזבנה קניה, V’neivid keivan de’zabna kinya,
it's like, what does, what is our concern that it's going to
work on שבת Shabbat if we sold it then it's gone, it
belongs to somebody else? גזירה משום שאילה ומשום שכירות. Gezeirah mishum she’ilah
u’mishum sechirut. It's,
it's a גזירה Gezeirah that extends, we're worried that if we allow
the sale, it's also going to make
lending and leasing, renting possible and therefore we're now, we're
now like going to be on some slippery slope. Challenge: שאילה קניא
ואגרה קניא, She’ilah kanya ve’agrah kanya, like,
and this is what's going to get unpacked in the next few
lines. Where, where is the boundary between borrowing and renting something? At
what point does it become yours and at what point it still
belongs to the owner? And I'm sure we can imagine it from
our own lives, like, you know, whatever, the place I live in
is mine, right, but there’s certain things that I can't do in
it. If I decide now to invite everybody to a ט"ו בשבט
Tu BiShvat planting in my living room and decide to dig a
hole there, probably not going to go over very well. Or if
I want to do a bonfire or so. Okay. So the inside
is mine, the outside still belongs to whoever it belongs. Similarly, when
we deal with renting and borrowing things between the Jews and the
non-Jews.
However, rather, the גמרא Gemara raises another option. אלא אמר רב בריה
דרמי בריה דרב ייבי גזירה משום נסיוני. Ella amar Rav breh Rami
breh de-Rav Yeivi gezeirah mishum nisiyoni. So the גזירה gezeirah is not
just on the leasing and renting, but because of this thing that's
called נסיוני. nisiyoni. נסיוני nisiyoni meaning testing. What do we mean by
testing? If I buy a car, right? Just before I buy it,
I'm going to want to test it. If I buy a big
animal, I'm going to want the owner to show me how well
it's doing, how is it carrying the load and all that. So,
what is the specific situation that the גמרא Gemara is worried about?
דזמנין
דזבנה לה ניהליה
סמוך לשקיעת החמה דמעלי שבתא. De-zamnin
de-zavna la nihaleih
samuch lishkiat hachamah de-ma'alei Shabta. But what if this whole transaction happens
close to sunset right near right near שבת? Shabbos? ואמר לו תא
ננסיה ניהלי דשמע לה קלה ואזלה מחמתיה.
Ve-amar lo ta nisyei nihali de-shama lei
kalia ve-azla meichamanteih.
So now I have this animal,
and the non-Jew wants to buy it. It's almost שבת. Shabbos. The
non-Jew wants me to show how well the animal is
doing—in Hebrew we say ביצועים, bitzuim, how well it's acting, showing up.
And it's going to hear—the animal is going to hear my voice
and it's like a voice-activated animal. By my voice, it's going to
be doing things.
We question whether a voice is an action or not,
but that's
what we're going to get to.
Yes. So this is what we're where we're at, right? בניחא ליה
דתיתי והוה ליה מחמר אחר בהמה בשבת והמחמר אחר בהמה בשבת חייב
חטאת.
Bi-nicha lei de-teita ve-hava lei mechamer achar behema be-Shabbat ve-hamichamer
achar behema be-Shabbat chayav chatat.
The concern is now that through my voice, I am activating an
animal to do something that it should not be doing on שבת
Shabbos under this prohibition of מחמר. mechamer. And
this
is considered a מלאכה melachah that now the animal is doing because
of me. I did not do anything, I did not turn on
the light or whatever, but I just said "come" and it's carrying,
and it's שבת Shabbos and now it is working. Okay, so this
תוספות Tosafot and the others are dealing with it, that this is
kind of a tight excuse.
Okay, because it's like a very specific action that happens only on
ערב שבת erev Shabbos and only if the sale is happening and
if I use my voice and all that. So we'll see that
we're trying to on one hand understand it but also go out
of it and have a broader view
on—just to zoom out to not lose the picture from the details
dealing with the fact that the משנה Mishnah told us not to
sell heavy animals to the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim around us. Okay.
מתקיף לה רב שישא בריה דרב אידי ושכירות מי קניא? Matkif lah
Rav Shisha breh de-Rav Idi usechirut mi kanya? So
again, back to the question of whether leasing is acquiring and
vice versa. והתנן אף במקום שאמרו להשכיר לא לבית דירה אמרו מפני
שמכניס לתוכו עבודת כוכבים.
Ve-hasnan af bimakom she-amru le-haskir
lo leveit dirah amru mipnei she-machnis letochoh avodat kochavim.
So we know from a משנה Mishnah that's going to come in
a few days on 21A
that even in a place where there is a permission to rent
stuff to a non-Jew, certain things we are limited on. For example,
the גמרא Gemara says: לא לבית דירה אמרו מפני שמכניס לתוכו עבודת
כוכבים. lo leveit dirah amru mipnei she-machnis letochoh avodat kochavim. We are
not allowed to rent an apartment to the non-Jew for the fear
of him bringing in עבודת כוכבים, avodat kochavim, idolatrous practice. So
what
yes? Like not an apartment? Okay, so maybe a shed or a
barn for an animal would be okay.
We could push back like how—and this is a whole discussion of
the דף daf in front of us. Where are the lines in
our interactions
vis-a-vis animals and stuff we have with the non-Jews around us? Because
you could say, okay, I shouldn't rent a non-Jew anything, right? Like,
what if he does this? What if he does this? So how
far how far are my boundaries and how far do I protect
myself? Okay, וסלקא דעתך v'salka da'atach שכירות קניא. sechirut kanya.
So here we were worried that he's going to bring idolatry, and
וסלקא דעתך v'salka da'atach שכירות קניא, sechirut kanya, if שכירות, sechirut,
if the leasing is like a buying, הא כי קא מייתי לביתיה
קא מייתי, ha ki ka maytei l'veiteh ka maytei, he's bringing it
into his own house, right? So what we mentioned just a minute
earlier, like how much of my place which I'm renting is actually
mine and how much is it still belonging to the owner, now
reversed with the Jew being the owner. שאני עבודה כוכבים דחמירא, shani
avodah kochavim d'chamira, דכתיב d'chtiv in דברים, Devarim, ולא תביא תועבה אל
ביתך. v'lo tavi toevah el beitecha. So we have a special stringency
around the issue of idolatrous practices because in דברים Devarim it tells
us do not bring, so it's not just don't do, right, or
don't practice, but don't even allow for idolatrous... this is not even
idolatrous, תועבה toevah really being something awful, disgusting, immoral, etc. Don't
allow like bringing this into into your home, as if the...
but once you've rented it to him it's no longer your home.
Well this is exactly the question but like, okay, huh?
Yeah no, you can obviously... it seems like it's the...
where are the lines? Like, you know, what kind of things can
I do in my rented place and what kind of things can't
I? Reverse if the Jew is the owner and the non-Jew is
the renter, what kind of things? So again I give the example
earlier, if I decided to have a bonfire in my living room
probably my owner would say no. If I decided to have a
loud party at 4 o'clock in the morning also probably they'd say
no. Here we're looking at the same but from a spiritual perspective,
which maybe is whatever, more ethereal but parallel. Okay, מתקיף לה, matkif
lah, there's a counter,
also objects to the the issue of leasing and ownership, where are
those lines? מתקיף לה רב יצחק בריה דרב משרשיא, matkif lah Rav
Yitzchak brei d'Rav Mesharsheya, בשכירות מי קניא, b'sechirut mi kanya,
again we're asking how much of leasing is like acquiring, והתנן, v'hatnan,
ישראל ששכר פרה מכהן, Yisrael she-sachar parah mi-kohen, יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה, yachilena
karshinei terumah, וכהן ששכר פרה מישראל, v'kohen she-sachar parah mi-yisrael, אף על
פי שמזונותיה עליו,
af al pi
she-mezonoteha alav, לא יאכילנה כרשיני תרומה. lo yachilena karshinei terumah.
We're bringing an example from תרומות Terumot which is interesting and it
says the following: ישראל, Yisrael, a Jew who's not a כהן, kohen,
not a לוי, Levi, who rented a cow from a כהן, kohen,
can feed her
כרשיני תרומה, karshinei terumah, the food of the תרומה. terumah.
כרשינה karshina is like a kind of a plant, we saw it
in שבת Shabbat when we studied, we're seeing it other places in
the תלמוד, Talmud, the text translates it as vetches, vetch. Whatever,
a kind of a grass or a legume that maybe was more
prevalent at that time, I can look into it more, but anyway.
Huh?
Being used for cattle fodder, but could also be used for humans,
so that's why
it's the כרשיני תרומה
karshinei terumah situation.
Okay,
not derailing. So if an ישראל Yisrael rents a cow from a
כהן kohen he can feed her from the תרומה. terumah. However, if
a כהן kohen rents a cow from ישראל, Yisrael, even though the
כהן kohen is obligated to feed this cow, he can't feed her
with the food of the תרומה, terumah, right? ואי סלקא דעתך שכירות
קניא, v'i salka da'atach sechirut kanya, אמאי לא יאכילנה פרה דידיה היא?
amai lo yachilena parah dideih hi? If you say that leasing is
like acquiring,
then why shouldn't he feed her? It's his cow so he can
feed her whatever is his, right? אלא שמע מינה שכירות לא קניא.
ela shma mina sechirut lo kanya. שכירות, sechirut, the leasing, is not
exactly like a purchase, so we're trying to find the lines where
it is. והשתא דאמרת שכירות לא קניא, v'hashta d'amart sechirut lo kanya,
גזירה משום שכירות, gzera mishum sechirut, וגזירה משום שאילה, u-gzera mishum she-elah,
וגזירה משום נסיוני. u-gzera mishum nisyonei.
And now that like we've proven that leasing and acquiring are not
exactly the same, then
therefore we extend from it a decree, גזירה, gzera, דרבנן, de-rabbanan, גזירה
gzera also to concerns of the שכירות sechirut we already said, שאילה
she-elah the lending, borrowing, and the נסיוני, nisyonei, this like occasions that
we are testing the animal, trial run. Trial run, yeah, we said
the test drive, when you buy a car nowadays
you test drive it or google.
Okay. חמרא לידא דספסירא. chamra l'yada d'sapsira. Okay, so רב אדא Rav
Adda allowed someone to sell
their donkey to a non-Jew through a ספסיר, sapsir, through a middleman,
middleman, sorry. And he gives us his reasons. אי משום ניסיוני, I
mishum nisyoni, if we are worried about the test drive business, הלא
ידע לקליה דאזל מחמתיה, halo yada l'kala d'azal mechmatei, so the middleman,
the animal does not know its voice, so this issue of test
drive through the voice is not going to happen. ואי משום שאלה
ושכירות, v'i mishum she'elah u'sechirut, כיוון דלאו דידיה, keivan d'lav didei, לא
מושיל ולא מוגר. lo moshil v'lo mogar. If you're worried about the
issues of lending and borrowing
and
leasing, because this donkey is not his, right, it doesn't belong to
the middleman, then he cannot lend it or lease it to somebody
else. ועוד, v'od, and additionally, משום דלא נגע לבי מומא, mishum d'la
naga l'vei muma, the middleman is not going to
do anything to it, it's not going to lease it or lease
it or lend it to somebody else because he doesn't want to
have any blemishes, he doesn't want any מום mum to happen to
this animal.
Okay, story. רב הונא זבינא ההיא פרה לעובד כוכבים. Rav Huna zabna
ha'i para l'oved kochavim.
Yeah, but what I don't understand, if the middleman, you know, is
really only acting as a proxy on the owner, so if the
guy wants, the purchaser says to the middleman, go tell the owner
I want a test drive, I don't understand. It's not like he
can't make a request.
Right, so first it's an okay, it's a case, right? רב אדא
Rav Adda allowed it.
I'm not sure I can answer everything. No, but you get what
I'm saying? Yes, so one issue is this is a case study,
right? רב אדא Rav Adda allowed it. So some people allowed it
and some people not allowed it. To the issue of ניסיוני, nisyoni,
I think it's a specific situation on this ערב שבת, erev Shabbat,
right?
Yeah, but it could still be שכירות? sechirut?
If the ספסיר sapsir is now dealing with the animal, it's not
going to
do what it says, it's not going to say, you know what,
I don't want to buy it, I want to rent it. Go
tell the, you know, go tell
the owner I, you know...
but
who's this 'go', who's telling?
The non-Jew can tell the middleman, go tell the owner I want
to rent it. So the middleman can't do it on his own,
but it's not like, you know, they don't communicate one with another.
Is this a, is
the middleman a Jewish man? Is it a, you know, has
a specific trade to make or where it's more like a wholesaler
where you know he's going to sell it, he's not the end
user, but you don't know who he's going to sell it to?
Yeah, this is a whole discussion that's going to come now of
who is the end user. Can you give it or sell it
to somebody who's then in turn going to like sell it or
give it to the wrong person? And I think some of that
discussion was yesterday when we talk about the לפני עיוור לא תיתן
מכשול, lifnei iver lo titein michshol, right? Do not place a stumbling
block before the blind person. So if I sell you something that
then in turn you're going to do something wrong with it, that's
on me, right? But what if I sell you something that you
then sell to somebody who is going to do something wrong with
it? This is like the לפני lifnei of the לפני, lifnei, how
much of it is still on me and how much can I
be like, well I don't know, I just sold it, I don't
know what happened to it? And you'll see a discussion between רבא
Rava and אביי Abaye where exactly this comes up of like...
yesterday I think אביי Abaye said you're not responsible two steps removed.
אביי Abaye said yesterday.
I think today is going to
worry about רבא. Rava. Let's just wait
for a minute.
Just because Rabbi Binish said that we do hold by that statement
of אביי Abaye yesterday, okay.
I don't know if that was a Jewish person or not when
Rabbi Binish said that, I didn't check.
Okay, if it's a Jewish person you should worry, if it's not
a Jewish person it changes a little bit, but then the question
is why are you selling it? You can't, we just said אין
מוכרין בהמה גסה, ein mocherin behemah gassah, you cannot sell the large
animal
to
the non-Jew. So what kind of a non-Jew? We'll see a distinction,
is it the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim or also the כותים, kutim,
the Samaritans? Okay, so these are exactly the boundaries that we're trying
to figure out. We're now in the mini story and we'll see
what רב הונא Rav Huna says about it. רב הונא Rav Huna
sold a cow to a עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. אמר ליה רב
חסדא, amar lei Rav Chisda, מאי טעמא עבד מר הכי? mai ta'ama
avad mar hachi? רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to him, why, master,
why did you do something like this? אמר ליה, amar lei, אימור
לשחיטה זבנה. eimor l'shechitah zabna. I can say that he's not buying
it in order to do something idolatrous, he's buying it in order
to eat.
So then why do we just say that before about the בהמה
גסה, behemah gassah, forget about the רביעה, reviya, just...
We said in the beginning, בהמה דקה behema daka we’re worried about
רביעה. revia. בהמה גסה behema gassa we’re not worried about רביעה. revia.
And if whatever if you think about it, that’s not, that’s not
the issue at hand.
Rumors from the Middle East, that usually not the issue with cows
and horses. The issues of bestiality is more with sheep, goats, little
animals that are with you in the field that you have more
control over. Hard to deal with a horse. Okay, let's see the
discussion around it.
Okay, רב הונא Rav Huna continues. ומנא תימא דאמרינן כהאי גוונא דתנן,
Umanat teima de'amrinan kehai gavna detnan, and
why, why do you say that, you know, like this,
רב הונא Rav Huna thinks that there is a קולא kula that,
you know, you can sell something that is going to be taken
to a שחיטה shchita and not to work. So we're going to
see if there's other examples that are similar to this. בית שמאי
לא ימכור אדם פרה חורשת בשביעית ובית הלל מתירין מפני שיכול לשוחטה.
Beit Shammai lo yimkor adam para choreshet bashvi'it u-Beit Hillel matirin mipnei
sheyachol leshochta. So we're bringing an example from another place in the
גמרא Gemara that בית שמאי Beit Shammai says a person may not
sell a cow that's going to work on the Sabbatical year, right,
on the שמיטה shmita year, because if you sell a person a
cow which is a plowing cow, most likely he might work it
on the Sabbatical year. You're now encouraging somebody to work on the
Sabbatical year. But בית הלל Beit Hillel allows such a sale because
we're not assuming things into why the owner bought the animal, ובית
הלל מתירין מפני שיכול לשוחטה. u-Beit Hillel matirin mipnei sheyachol leshochta.
So this is the opinion that we accept. You can assume that
the animal will be used for something permitted rather than a forbidden
person, forbidden purpose, okay. Okay, אמר רבא מי דמי? Amar Rava mi
dami?
Is this, is this like really the same? Can we really compare
this usage of animals on שמיטה shmita to the usage of animals
on שבת, Shabbat, which is what we started with, right, that we're
concerned with the non-Jew making the animal work on שבת? Shabbat? What
is the problem with this? What are our commandments vis-a-vis animals on
שביעי, shvi'i, on שמיטה? shmita?
We don't have any. What are our commandments about animals on שבת?
Shabbat?
Must rest. Right, so okay, this is exactly what רבא Rava said.
מי דמי? Mi dami? Are they similar? התם אין אדם מצווה על
שביתת בהמתו בשביעית והכא אדם מצווה על שביתת בהמתו בשבת. Hatam ein
adam mitzuveh al shvitat behemto bashvi'it vehacha adam mitzuveh al shvitat behemto
beShabbat. So
in the שמיטה shmita we're not commanded on having the animal rest,
we're commanded to have the land rest. In the on שבת Shabbat
we are commanded to have the animal rest.
Okay, אמר ליה אביי וכל היכא דאדם מצווה אסור? Amar lei Abaye
vechol heicha de'adam mitzuveh assur? Everywhere,
does that mean that everywhere where a person is commanded to let
his possessions, let his stuff rest, then we can't sell him an
item that he might do labor with it? So then we do
have an example from the שמיטה. shmita. והרי שדה דאדם מצווה על
שביתת שדהו בשביעית ותנן בית שמאי לא ימכור אדם שדה ניר בשביעית
ובית הלל מתירין מפני שיכול להובירה.
Veharei sadeh de'adam mitzuveh al shvitat sadehu bashvi'it vetnan Beit
Shammai lo yimkor adam sadeh nir bashvi'it u-Beit Hillel matirin mipnei sheyachol
lehovirah. So if we extend from it
to
our our concern around things that the person might be using that
it's like the that we or I'm missing something, that if this
means that wherever a person is commanded to allow their possessions to
rest, he cannot sell them an item, right, that they might do
a labor that they shouldn't be doing, like on on שבת, Shabbat,
then we have a case of a field, right? The animal is
not a good example on the Sabbatical year, but a field might
be. בית שמאי Beit Shammai say a person should not sell somebody
שדה ניר, sadeh nir, a field that is plowed and ready for
seeding, but בית הלל Beit Hillel allow because you can use it
not this year but next year. So I can sell you the
field now but to use it in the future year. So we
brought a case that although one is commanded to let the field
rest during the Sabbatical year, you can still sell it under the
assumption that the buyer will do with it something permitted in the
year after. מתקיף לה רב אשי, Matkif lah Rav Ashi, רב אשי
Rav Ashi doesn't like it. וכל היכא דאין אדם מצווה שרי? Vechol
heicha de'ein adam mitzuveh shari? Is it true that wherever there's no
מצווה mitzvah specifically
to rest their possessions then we are allowed to sell an item?
והרי כלים, Veharei kelim, we do have tools. instructions regarding some vessels,
some tools. דאין אדם מצווה על שביתת כלים בשביעית. D'ein adam mitzuveh
al shevitat keilim b'Shevi'it. A person is not commanded to have their
tools rest on the Sabbatical year, right? Only the land. But the
משנה Mishna tells us, there is a משנה Mishna in another place,
דתנן. d'tnan. ואלו כלים שאין אדם רשאי למוכרן בשביעית. V'eilu keilim she'ein
adam rashai l'mochran b'Shevi'it. There is a משנה Mishna that tells us
specifically: these are tools that should not be sold on the Sabbatical.
המחרשה וכל כליה, Hamachresha v'chol keileha, האול, ha'ol, והמזרע, v'hamizre'a, והדקר. v'hadakar.
The plow and all its attachments,
האול, ha'ol, the yoke, which is used to hitch the cows to
the plow, and המזרע, hamizre'a, the winnowing fork, like to spread things
around, and the stake. Not sure what that does.
Make holes in the ground.
Make holes in the ground. הדקר hadakar from like poking. Thank you.
אלא אמר רב אשי. Ella amar Rav Ashi. So, so we have
not quite been able to prove it this way because we were
okay selling a field, we're okay selling a cow on שמיטה, Shmita,
we're not okay selling certain tools. אלא אמר רב אשי. Ella amar
Rav Ashi. כל היכא דאיכא למתלי תלינן Kol heicha d'ika lemitli talinan
ואף על גב דמצווה v'af al gav d'mitzuveh וכל היכא דליכא למתלי
לא תלינן v'chol heicha d'leika d'mitli lo talinan אף על גב דאינו
מצווה. af al gav d'eino mitzuveh. This needs to be read a
few times and I'm wondering how far we can take it. Gloria
and I can struggle with this later. Basically,
the גמרא Gemara tells us: anywhere that it is possible למתלי, lemitli,
to hang something, like to assign an innocent motive, to hang the
motive on something else, then we do that, right? When we can
say, no, this cow is going to be used for שחיטה, shechita,
don't worry, it's not this, it's not going to be worked,
then we use, we assign such a motive, even though, even though
one
is commanded to, in this example, to allow this item to rest.
In anywhere that it's not possible, וכל היכא דליכא למתלי, v'chol heicha
d'leika d'mitli, where we have no possibility to hang on such a
motive, then we don't, even though one is not commanded. So this
is, this would be interesting to see how far this carries in
the place where we can find a כולה kula to work with
the situation we do, and in a place where we can't, we
can't. Okay, and now we have this situation between רבה Rabbah and
אביי. Abaye.
Okay,
רבה Rabbah and אביי. Abaye. רבה זבין ההוא חמרא לישראל החשיד למכור
לעובד כוכבים. Rabbah zavin hahu chamra l'Yisrael hachashid limkor l'oved kochavim. So
רבה Rabbah sold this donkey to a Jew who is suspect, suspected
of selling animals to idolaters.
This is David, your situation. Right? I think.
So we have רבה, Rabbah, yeah, רבה, Rabbah, whatever, פלוני אלמוני, ploni
almoni, and the
idolaters. אמר לו אביי: Amar lo Abaye: מאי טעמא עבד מר הכי?
Mai ta'ama avad mar hachi? Why, רבה, Rabbah, how did you do
this? This would be great to act out. אמר לו: Amar lo:
אנא לישראל זביני. Ana l'Yisrael zavini. Me? I'm doing business with Jews,
right? I just sold to a Jew. אמר לו: Amar lo: והא
אזיל ומזבין ליה לעובד כוכבים. v'ha azil u'mzavin lei l'oved kochavim.
But he's going to go out and sell it to the idolater.
רבה Rabbah says: לעובד כוכבים קא מזבין לישראל לא קא מזבין? L'oved
kochavim ka mzavin l'Yisrael lo ka mzavin? Like, this is what you're
worried about? You're worried that he's going to sell it to an
idolater? But he can just as same sell it to a Jew.
So we don't know who he's going to sell it to. You
mean I can't do business with anybody because there is maybe a
possibility
that he's going to sell it to a non-Jew? Let me do
the spoiler for maybe easier following on this intense conversation between these
two friends. רבה Rabbah is accepting a כולה kula on himself by
selling it to somebody that it is not a responsible thing to
sell it to, and אביי Abaye is going to challenge him sufficiently
until רבה Rabbah is going to change his mind. Okay, so if
it's a little bit confusing, it's because it's going to go back.
But basically,
let's say we have, we have an instance, right? רבה, Rabbah,
right?
And he sells to a Jew who might sell... to
a... how would we do an idolater? Stars. עובד כוכבים. Oved Kochavim.
Okay?
And אביי Abbaye says this is an important thing, you can't sell
to somebody who might misuse the item sell and we'll see and
well we'll get there, you'll see discussion about can we sell the
non-Jews weapons?
But this is what I was going to say about the previous
discussion not current
I just want to say
yeah
the difference between in אביי's Abbaye the discussion yesterday about אביי, Abbaye,
he was selling to a non-Jew. Okay. So here we're selling to
a Jew. So that's the difference. Now then you just said something
right now about questioning selling to a non-Jew, but that's the... Yes.
So am I, am I responsible of look how far where is
this going to end up?
Yes, am I responsible of look how far where is this going
to end up?
But at least like like a grandchild of my transaction. Right. Like
am I responsible just for this and I'm like hey
I sold it to a
Jew or let's say I sold it to somebody responsible who turned
around and sells my weapons to never mind I didn't mean to
say anything
but as a like an Israeli TV show now that has lots
of plots but one of them is an Israeli businessman who's selling
weapons in Thailand seemingly not a problem right but
who knows where that ends up?
Right. So how far are we responsible to our transactions? Okay.
And we'll see that one of the issues that sits in the
back of our minds is this issue of לפני עור לא תתן
מכשול. Lifnei iver lo titein michshol.
לפני עור. Lifnei iver. Right? Do not put a stumbling block before
the blind person. Okay. So if I sold something that this person
then is going to sell, he's obligated not to stumble somebody else.
He's obligated not to stumble but he's not.
So so where is this you know where is this flow going?
And we'll see in a minute whether that's a Jew in the
middle or
not.
That matters. That matters.
It matters.
And we'll see another situation in just a minute of this person,
okay, Jew selling to a non-Jew selling to selling to a
non-Jew who's a כותי Cutie
who accepts the written Torah right as a resident of the land
accepting the written Torah not accepting the oral tradition. Is this different
now? Do we have different levels of non-Jews what we can sell?
All right.
So the other thing is in the second one is that question
mark or is that you know for sure who he sells to?
This is you'll see just like we had yesterday at the end
of the day and the beginning kind of mention of today מקום
שנהגו מקום שלא נהגו makom shenahagu makom shelo nahagu is that we
have a מנהג minhag where about the בהמה גסה behemah gassah to
a non-Jew to an idolater a hefty animal to an idolater always
not allowed and now we're trying to work around this because רבא
Rava has his donkey but with the כותים Cutim we have a
different relationship. Stay tuned.
This all would live much better in a chart with pictures and
all that but but. Okay. So רבא Rava raises an objection to
what sorry אביי Abbaye raises an objection to what רבא Rava just
did.
Pushing רבא Rava on this thing רבא Rava just sold a donkey
to a Jew who's suspected of selling to idolaters. Okay. איתיבי Eitvei
רבא Rava brings an objection from a ברייתא. baraita. מקום שנהגו למכור
בהמה דקה לכותים מוכרים שלא למכור אין מוכרים מאי טעמא? Makom shenahagu
limkor behemah dakah lekutim mocherim shelo limkor ein mocherim mai taama? A
place where it is custom to sell small livestock בהמה דקה behemah
dakah to the כותים Cutim to the Samaritans they're still there to
this day one may sell the animal to them but in a
place where this is not the custom one may not. מאי טעמא?
Mai taama? What is the reason
that possibly the sale of small animals in some places to the
כותים Cutim is
forbidden? אילימא משום דחשידי ארבויי מחשידי? Ileiima mishum dechashidi arviia mechashidi? If
you say that it is because of bestiality are they suspected? They
are they're like a semi semi-Jewish category so we look at them
differently. והתניא אין מעמידין בהמה בפונדקאות של עובדי כוכבים זכרים אצל זכרים
ונקבות אצל נקבות ואין צריך לומר נקבות אצל זכרים וזכרים אצל נקבות.
Vehatanya ein maamidin behemah befundekaot shel ovedei kochavim zecharim eitzel zecharim unekevot
eitzel nekevot
ve-ein tzarich lomar nekevot eitzel zecharim uzecharim eitzel nekevot.
If You take it from where it is taught that one does
not keep an animal in the inns of the עובדי כוכבים. ovdei
kokhavim. Notice it can get a little confused distinguishing between the עובדי
כוכבים ovdei kokhavim and the כותים. kutim. Then, okay, the male with
the male and the female with the female, but no need to
say of course female with males and males with females.
Any situation that is a possible רביעה. reviah. If you want to
get really into the gory details of this, which maybe you don't,
but רש"י Rashi does, so take it with רש"י Rashi afterwards.
רש"י Rashi asks, "Okay, we got all the variations of
male-male, male-female, female-male. But what about the female-female? Like there's no possibility
of רביעה." reviah. And they're like, "Okay, somebody else may come or
may walk into the scene and therefore be able to use the
animal." Okay, ואין מוסרים בהמה לרועה שלהם. ve-ein mosrim behemah le-ro'eh shelahem.
This is semi-review. ואין מיחדים עמהם. ve-ein meyachadin imahem. All with the
idolaters, we don't give them animals, our animals to their shepherds, and
we don't have
ייחוד. yichud. ואין מוסרים להם תינוק ללמדו ספר ve-ein mosrim lahem tinok
le-lamdo sefer וללמדו אומנות. u-le-lamdo amnut.
Learn a trade. אבל, aval, אבל, aval, מעמידין בהמה בפונדקאות של כותים,
ma'amidin behemah be-pundekaot shel kutim, זכרים אצל נקבות ונקבות אצל זכרים, zakharim
etzel nekevot u-nekevot etzel zakharim, ואין צריך לומר זכרים אצל זכרים ונקבות
אצל נקבות. ve-ein tsarikh lomar zakharim etzel zakharim u-nekevot etzel nekevot. We
trust the Samaritans. We trust the כותים. kutim. We don't treat them
the same like the idolaters because they accept on themselves the תורה
שבכתב. Torah she-bikhtav.
Just not the תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-be'al peh, but the תורה
שבכתב Torah she-bikhtav they accept. ומוסרים, u-mosrim, continue,
ומוסרים בהמה לרועה שלהם, u-mosrim behemah le-ro'eh shelahem, ומיחדים עמהם, u-meyachadin imahem,
ומוסרים להם תינוק ללמדו ספר, u-mosrim lahem tinok le-lamdo sefer, וללמדו אומנות.
u-le-lamdo amnut. אלמא לא חשידי. alma lo chashidi. So
if
we do all these things with the כותי, kuti, right? We entrust
our animals to them and our children and our having them teach
them reading and a craft, then supposedly the כותים kutim are not
suspected of engaging in bestiality. And yet, and yet, and yet, this
is all in regarding to בהמה דקה. behemah dakkah.
We trust them, that's okay. But בהמה גסה behemah gassah we worry.
Why? Because if we sell it here, if we sell it here
or even if we sell it here, he might go and sell
it here. He might turn around and sell it to the non-Jews.
Only the large animals.
The large animals, we're not worried about him with the small animal
because he accepts the תורה, Torah, therefore he's not going to mistreat
it as bestiality. But with the big animals we worry, because it
started, our משנה mishna started by saying, "אין מוכרין להם בהמה גסה,
ein mokhrin lahem behemah gassah, period." Not a מנהג minhag some places
yes some places no, but this is a no.
I reiterate what I said in the beginning, there may be an
undertone to it that's not even mentioned, maybe because it's so obvious,
that the בהמה דקה behemah dakkah belongs to nomadic people, so they
come and go, whereas the בהמה גסה behemah gassah belongs to people
that will root themselves in the land. So by selling them heavy
livestock, we encourage their being in the land. So this is not
just their practices, but their presence. Maybe. Okay, this is not, it's
not appearing in the text, but a lot of the undercurrent in
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is our presence with the non-Jews and definitely
our presence vis-a-vis the land of Israel.
Okay, ועוד תניא, ve-od tanya, and furthermore, so as taught in the
ברייתא, brayta, and you just said it a few minutes ago, "אין
מוכרין להם לא זיין ולא כלי זיין ואין משחיזין להם את הזיין
ואין מוכרין להם לא סדן ולא קולרין ולא כבלים ולא שלשלאות של
ברזל אחד עובדי כוכבים ואחד כותים."
ein mokhrin lahem lo zayin ve-lo klei zayin ve-ein mashchizin lahem et
ha-zayin ve-ein mokhrin lahem lo sadan ve-lo kularin ve-lo kevalim ve-lo shalshelaot
shel
barzel echad ovdei kokhavim ve-echad kutim. So okay, we trust them, the
כותים, kutim, we trust with our animals, however
we're not selling them weapons or any attachments
to the weapons, like let's say the sword and the place that
the sword is hanging from, or sharpening weapons for them, or selling
them סדן sadan is leg locks that you put on slaves, and
קולרין, kularin, collar,
right, collar for neck chains, and כבלים. kavalim. Same word in Hebrew,
קולר.
kular. כן כן. ken ken.
But
it could be that it traveled.
כבלים. kavalim. כבלים. kavalim. Yeah, same thing.
It'd be interesting to look at it, like how far back, like
is this word coming from? Is it a slave trade thing that
went around? But even today for a dog if you have a
collar.
קולר, kolar, yeah.
Okay, or foot chain or iron chain. This and this applies both
to the gentiles and the כותים. Kutim. Just a second, Gemara will
unpack and come back to Rabbah and Abaye. We haven't yet finished
their conversation. מאי טעמא? אי נימא דחשידי אשפיכות דמים? ומי חשידי? Mai
ta'ama? I nima dechashidi ashfichut damim? Umi chashidi? If, what,
what is the reason that we don't sell them all these things?
If,
especially to the, to the כותים, Kutim, if we say that they
are suspected of killing people, right? That's difficult because
if
you just told me a minute ago that we can have ייחוד
yichud with them and we trust our children with them, right? So
this does not make sense that we worry about them that they're
like blood-shedders, right? Rather, אלא משום דאתי לזבונה
לעובדי כוכבים. Ela mishum
de'ati lezavona
le'ovdei kochavim. Just
a second, I didn't finish the sentence. Okay. אי נימא דחשידי אשפיכות
דמים? ומי חשידי? הא אמרת מתייחדין עמהם?
I nima dechashidi ashfichut damim? Umi
chashidi? Ha amrat mityachdin imahem?
Right, like
what are we suspecting? We just said that we can have ייחוד
yichud with them and animals and all that. אלא משום דאתי לזבונה
לעובדי כוכבים. Ela mishum de'ati lezavona le'ovdei kochavim. But rather we're not
allowed to sell them items because they in turn are going to
sell them to the עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. And this is still
part of Abaye's answer to Rabbah saying just like we cannot sell
to the כותי Kuti who will then sell to the עובד כוכבים,
ovved kochavim, maybe you cannot sell to the Jew who maybe will
sell it to the עובד כוכבים. ovved kochavim. And further, וכי תימא:
כותי לא עביד תשובה, ישראל עביד תשובה. Vechi teima: Kuti lo avid
teshuvah, Yisrael avid teshuvah. You might say, or maybe Rabbah is saying,
okay, the כותי Kuti might not do a תשובה, teshuvah, but the
Jew can do תשובה. teshuvah. I will sell it to the Jew,
yes, though he is suspected of selling it to the idolaters, but
maybe he will just do תשובה teshuvah right now and change his
mind. והאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה: כדרך שאמרו אסור. Veha'amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha: Kederech she'amru asur.
So we have Rav Nachman,
Abaye brings us what Rav Nachman says, which is what we say,
right? This is our accepted practice. כדרך שאמרו אסור למכור לעובד כוכבים,
כך אסור למכור לישראל החשוד למכור לעובד כוכבים.
Kederech she'amru asur limkor le'ovved
kochavim, kach asur limkor leYisrael hachashud limkor le'ovved kochavim. Just like we
forbid people to sell these kind of items to an idolater, we
also forbid you, anyone, selling to a Jew
who
might sell it to the idolater. This is the לפני עור לא
תתן מכשול Lifnei iver lo titein michshol and now you are putting
a מכשול michshol in front of this person by giving them an
item that they might want to sell. רהיט בתריה תלתא
פרסי.
Rahit batrei tlata
parsei. I know I did not...
רהיט בתריה תלתא פרסי. Rahit batrei tlata parsei.
And some say פרסה בחלא ולא אדרכיה. Parsa bechala velo adrachei. Rabbah,
now understanding he made a mistake, he heard this whole reasoning of
Abaye and Rav Nachman's ruling on this, realizing he made a mistake,
he ran three פרסאות parsa'ot after this Jew to whom he sold
the donkey. And some say he ran only one פרסה parsa but
he did that in sand, i.e., very hard. פרסה Parsa is two
thousand מיל mil and
from what I saw about four kilometers, so what is it like
three, close to three miles? Twelve kilometers, eight, nine, what does he
say?
It says here between 7.2 and 8.7 miles.
I'm close with my thing, around eight miles, right? And some say
only three miles but in sand.
ולא אדרכיה. Velo adrachei. But he didn't, he wasn't able to catch
him. Nevertheless, we have our ruling, right? We cannot sell to somebody
who we suspect might sell it to somebody who will misuse it.
Okay. אמר רב ביבי בר אבא: כדרך שאסור למכור לעובד כוכבים, אסור
למכור ללסטים ישראל. היכי דמי? אי דחשיד דקטיל, פשיטא היינו עובד כוכבים!
Okay,
so now Rav Bibi bar Abba is extending it. He says just
like we're not allowed... To sell to a gentile, we also cannot
sell to a לסטים *listim* who is a Jew, to a bandit
who is a Jew. Why, why are you saying this? What are
exactly היכי דמי *Heichi dami*, what are the circumstances of it? If,
like, he's suspected of killing, right? If he's a לסטים *listim* and
he's suspected of killing, then isn't it like it's obvious that it's
not we can't allow selling it to them.
So then he's פשיטא *pshita*, he's just like another idolater, right? He's
going to misuse the item and we can't give it to him.
ואי דלא קטיל קטיל אמאי לא *ve'ei de'lo katil katil amai lo*?
לעולם דלא קטיל *le'olam de'lo katil*. והכא במאי עסקינן *ve'hacha be'mai askinan*,
what are we talking about? So
if this is a לסטים *listim*, a bandit who does not kill,
why not sell it to him, right? It's a bandit who only
specializes in what...
robbery, okay...
stealing things, but he's like, you know, murder is not his thing.
Okay. והכא במאי עסקינן *ve'hacha be'mai askinan*, what are we dealing in?
במשמוטא דזימנין דעביד לאצולי נפשה *be'mashmuta de'zimnin de'avid le'atzolei nafsha*. We're dealing
with somebody who steals and he only needs the weapon in order
to protect himself just in case. But we can't sell it to
him because he's, like, the weapon is what makes him feel strong
because of the assumption that if push comes to shove, he will
use it. We're going to continue just a little bit further.
Okay.
Okay. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. אין מוכרין להם תריסים ויש אומרים מוכרין
להם תריסים *Ein mochrin lahem trisim ve'yesh omrim mochrin lahem trisim*. We
have two
teachings,
two conflicting teachings, and maybe we can ask about it more tomorrow
because it doesn't quote to us...
I find it unusual, right? אין מוכרין להם תריסים ויש אומרים מוכרין
להם *Ein mochrin lahem trisim ve'yesh omrim mochrin lahem*. We don't sell,
like, shields, protective items to the non-Jews
even though these are items that are used for protection, not for
attack. But some say, yes, you can sell them shields. מאי טעמא
*Mai ta'ama*, what is the reason to not sell? אילימא משום דמגינו
עלייהו *eileima mishum de'meginu aleihu*, אי הכי אפילו חיטי ושערי נמי לא
*ei hachi afilu chiti u'se'ari nami lo*. So if
why, what is the reason behind this opinion that
forbids us from selling shields to the gentiles? If we say that
it's because they protect themselves in wartime, then we will say that
we can't sell anything to them, right? We can't even sell wheat
and barley, חיטי ושערי *chiti u'se'ari* should not be sold to them.
רב סבר *Rav savar*, אי אפשר הכי נמי *ee efshar hachi nami*.
If it's possible, if it were, and I think this is
kind of the crux of it, right? If it was possible to
avoid selling
anything, produce or whatever to them without incurring their animosity, then it
would have been forbidden to do so. Like if we could minimize
our interaction and not incur animosity from the people around them, then
we would do that. But limiting our sales to such an extent
would cause great harm in every possible level in our interactions and
our economy and the feeling of people around us and nothing current,
but we can see what happens with people that are overly isolated
and like how the world is looking at that situation. So therefore
we allow some interaction that we can, you know, that we can
possibly do. We don't want to give them things for their idolatrous
behavior or weapons for war, but the things that are like in
between, the protective items or the חיטי ושערי *chiti u'se'ari*, yes, we
allow this. איכא דאמרי *Ika de'amri*, תריסים היינו טעמא דלא דחשילי וזינא
נינהו וקטלי בהו גוים *trisim hainu ta'ama de'lo de'chashili ve'zina ninhu ve'katli
behu goyim*. So some say those that have the shields,
one reason not to sell it, not to allow to sell it
to the non-Jews is
that
their use in weapon is for battle, right? זינא הוא *zina hu*
for
like
arms. They will kill with the shields. The shields can be used
for protection, but they can be also used like as... metal I'm
assuming for attack. And according to יש אומרים מוכרים להם תריסים וכי
שלים זיין ומארקא רקי mochrim lahem trissim v'chi shalim zayin u'marka raki
and the other reason is that some say that if you sell
them the shields, the
it's not a concern because they use them to flee, לערוק, la'arok,
they use them to
protect
themselves and escape so not for war. אמר רב נחמן בר אבא
בר אבוה הלכה כיש אומרים. Amar Rav Nachman bar Abba bar Avuha
halacha k'yesh omrim. The הלכה halacha is as the latter opinion that
it's possible to sell them in in a with a benefit of
doubt and hopes that this will turn out for the best and
not for the worst. We're at the top of טז Tes Zayin
five lines from the top and I am going to pause with
your permission.
Hope everybody has a fabulous day. Thank you for being with us
this morning.
You might
tell